<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Author: Robert Basic - ZF Blog</title>
    <description>Author: Robert Basic - ZF Blog</description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2013 09:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2.0.6 (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://framework.zend.com/blog/author/robertbasic.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://framework.zend.com/blog/author/robertbasic-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Help us improve the documentation!</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2013 09:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://framework.zend.com/blog/2013-03-28-help-us-improve-the-documentation.html</link>
      <guid>http://framework.zend.com/blog/2013-03-28-help-us-improve-the-documentation.html</guid>
      <author>robertbasic.com@gmail.com (Robert Basic)</author>
      <dc:creator>Robert Basic</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    A piece of software is only as good as its documentation. The Zend 
    Framework team and a dozen or so contributors are working hard to 
    improve the Zend Framework 2 documentation, but we still want <em>you</em> 
    to help us improve it even more. Any kind of help is welcome and greatly 
    appreciated.
</p>

<p>
    First of all, you don't have to have a major in English literature to help 
    us with the documentation. We, the contributors, come from all over the 
    world and many of us use English as a second &mdash; or even third! &mdash; 
    language, but that does not stop us from trying to improve the docs. Neither 
    should it stop you.
</p>

<p>
    We are not asking for much. Read a chapter or two, or 
    even just a paragraph. Point us to parts of the documentation that are 
    confusing, unclear, or not explained well enough. Would it be easier for you 
    to understand a section if we would add a picture or two? <em>Tell us.</em> Do you 
    want to see more code examples? <em>Let us know.</em> Pick a component that you use 
    most often and work with the contributors to have the documentation for 
    that component as clear as possible. Have something to add? <em>Send a pull 
    request.</em>
</p>

<p>
    We all learn in different ways, and while some documentation might be good for one 
    developer, it might be confusing for another. That's why we are striving to 
    have several different ways of presenting the material: reference manual, 
    tutorials, user guides, API docs. Let us know what works best for you and 
    we will do our best to make it happen.
</p>

<p>
    We would like to ask you one thing, though. Any and all problems, requests, 
    ideas you have that can help us improve the documentation, please report 
    them on <a href="https://github.com/zendframework/zf2-documentation/issues">the documentation issue 
    tracker on Github</a>. Thanks!
</p><p>
    If you'd like to start contributing to the documentation by submitting 
    patches and improvements, the best place to start is to read the <a 
    href="https://github.com/zendframework/zf2-documentation/blob/master/CONTRIBUTING.md">contributing 
    guide</a>.
</p>

<p>
    Just so you know that we do really work on improving the documentation, a 
    week or so ago we held our first dochunt. It was a weekend dedicated to 
    improving the documentation and <a href="https://gist.github.com/Bittarman/27575710b347bdb73631">as you can 
    see from the results</a> quite a few fixes and improvements were made,
    thanks to those who participated. In the coming weeks, we will hold the next 
    dochunt. This time we will try to strictly focus on writing new tutorial and 
    improving existing ones, but any and all contributions are welcomed.
</p>

<p>
    We don't know yet when the second dochunt will be held, but we will let you 
    know. Until then, <a href="http://framework.zend.com/manual/2.1/en/index.html">start reading 
    through the manual</a>, look for things to improve, keep a list of what's missing, and 
    <a href="https://github.com/zendframework/zf2-documentation/issues">give us 
    feedback</a>!
</p>

<p>
    The contributors and the Zend Framework team thank you!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
