<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Author: Robert Basic - ZF Blog</title>
  <updated>2013-03-28T09:15:00+00:00</updated>
  <generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="2">Zend_Feed_Writer</generator>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://framework.zend.com/blog/author/robertbasic.html"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://framework.zend.com/blog/author/robertbasic-atom.xml"/>
  <id>http://framework.zend.com/blog/author/robertbasic.html</id>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Help us improve the documentation!]]></title>
    <published>2013-03-28T09:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-03-28T09:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://framework.zend.com/blog/2013-03-28-help-us-improve-the-documentation.html"/>
    <id>http://framework.zend.com/blog/2013-03-28-help-us-improve-the-documentation.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Robert Basic</name>
      <email>robertbasic.com@gmail.com</email>
      <uri>http://robertbasic.com/</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>A piece of software is only as good as its documentation. The
Zend Framework team and a dozen or so contributors are working hard
to improve the Zend Framework 2 documentation, but we still want
<xhtml:em>you</xhtml:em> to help us improve it even more. Any kind of help is
welcome and greatly appreciated.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>First of all, you don't have to have a major in English
literature to help us with the documentation. We, the contributors,
come from all over the world and many of us use English as a second
— or even third! — language, but that does not stop us from trying
to improve the docs. Neither should it stop you.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>We are not asking for much. Read a chapter or two, or even just
a paragraph. Point us to parts of the documentation that are
confusing, unclear, or not explained well enough. Would it be
easier for you to understand a section if we would add a picture or
two? <xhtml:em>Tell us.</xhtml:em> Do you want to see more code examples?
<xhtml:em>Let us know.</xhtml:em> Pick a component that you use most often and
work with the contributors to have the documentation for that
component as clear as possible. Have something to add? <xhtml:em>Send a
pull request.</xhtml:em></xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>We all learn in different ways, and while some documentation
might be good for one developer, it might be confusing for another.
That's why we are striving to have several different ways of
presenting the material: reference manual, tutorials, user guides,
API docs. Let us know what works best for you and we will do our
best to make it happen.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>We would like to ask you one thing, though. Any and all
problems, requests, ideas you have that can help us improve the
documentation, please report them on <xhtml:a href="https://github.com/zendframework/zf2-documentation/issues">the
documentation issue tracker on Github</xhtml:a>. Thanks!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>If you'd like to start contributing to the documentation by
submitting patches and improvements, the best place to start is to
read the <xhtml:a href="https://github.com/zendframework/zf2-documentation/blob/master/CONTRIBUTING.md">
contributing guide</xhtml:a>.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Just so you know that we do really work on improving the
documentation, a week or so ago we held our first dochunt. It was a
weekend dedicated to improving the documentation and <xhtml:a href="https://gist.github.com/Bittarman/27575710b347bdb73631">as you can
see from the results</xhtml:a> quite a few fixes and improvements were
made, thanks to those who participated. In the coming weeks, we
will hold the next dochunt. This time we will try to strictly focus
on writing new tutorial and improving existing ones, but any and
all contributions are welcomed.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>We don't know yet when the second dochunt will be held, but we
will let you know. Until then, <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/manual/2.1/en/index.html">start reading
through the manual</xhtml:a>, look for things to improve, keep a list of
what's missing, and <xhtml:a href="https://github.com/zendframework/zf2-documentation/issues">give us
feedback</xhtml:a>!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The contributors and the Zend Framework team thank you!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
