<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>DevZone - Items tagged as: Zend_Framework_Developer</title>
        <link>http://devzone.zend.com/</link>
        <description>advancing the art of PHP.  Best practices, samples, articles, news, and community for PHP 4, PHP 5, and beyond.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2010 15:46:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2010 15:46:39 +0000</pubDate>
        <docs>http://devzone.zend.com/tag/Zend_Framework_Developer/format/rss2.0</docs>     
        <language>en-us</language> 
        <image>
          <title>DevZone - Items tagged as: Zend_Framework_Developer</title>
          <link>http://devzone.zend.com/</link>
          <url>http://devzone.zend.com/images/devzone_logo4.gif</url>
        </image>
                  <item>
            <title>Flex and Zend Framework - Part 1</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2010 15:46:39 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
	It would be a fair statement to say that I have not paid attention to Flash for several years. Obviously I know that those awesome interfaces for movie web sites are made in flash, as are those annoying video ads that start screaming at you as soon as you load up a page, competing with Megadeth on Rhapsody, cranked out on the 700 watts of power I have in my office. But the last time I really looked seriously at Flash was almost a decade ago and I was thrilled at tweening widgets from one place to another. Unfortunately, there&#39;s not really any benefit to tweening a text box. Cool? Yes. Practical? No. So I never really picked it up. Plus I was cheap. 
 
	That is the reason why I had not really been paying attention to Flash for the past several years. I generally don&#39;t look into something if it&#39;s cool. I look into something if it is practical. Flash, generally, is meant to be, well, flashy. And it is. But for someone such as myself, I didn&#39;t think I had much of a reason to pay attention. Until now... 
 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/12013-Flex-and-Zend-Framework---Part-1</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/12013-Flex-and-Zend-Framework---Part-1</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Brandon Savage&#039;s Blog: Making Zend_Navigation Useful</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2010 15:11:52 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
As a follow-up to his  previous post  on Zend_Navigation  Brandon Savage  takes a look at how to  make it more useful  by using some of the methods that come bundled with the component.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/12011-Brandon-Savages-Blog-Making-Zend_Navigation-Useful</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/12011-Brandon-Savages-Blog-Making-Zend_Navigation-Useful</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Brandon Savage&#039;s Blog: The Adventures Of Merging Propel With Zend Framework</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2010 16:40:30 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
In a new post to his blog  Brandon Savage  takes a quick loook at hos he  integrated Propel into a Zend Framework app  he'd built to replace an older site.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/12009-Brandon-Savages-Blog-The-Adventures-Of-Merging-Propel-With-Zend-Framework</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/12009-Brandon-Savages-Blog-The-Adventures-Of-Merging-Propel-With-Zend-Framework</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Ibuildings techPortal: Zend Studio formatted for Zend Framework and ATK</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2010 10:58:13 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
On the Ibuildings techPortal site today  Ivo Jansch  takes a look at a type formatter they've created to work with Zend Studio to more correctly format your code as per the  official coding standard  for the Zend Framework.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/12007-Ibuildings-techPortal-Zend-Studio-formatted-for-Zend-Framework-and-ATK</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/12007-Ibuildings-techPortal-Zend-Studio-formatted-for-Zend-Framework-and-ATK</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Brandon Savage&#039;s Blog: Learning Zend Framework: A Case Study</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2010 15:48:48 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
Recently  Brandon Savage  has been really getting into the Zend Framework and creating applications with it. He, like many other developers just starting out with this framework, has had his share of frustrations. In the latest post to his blog  Brandon  looks at some of these  first steps  and what he's learned from them.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/12001-Brandon-Savages-Blog-Learning-Zend-Framework-A-Case-Study</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/12001-Brandon-Savages-Blog-Learning-Zend-Framework-A-Case-Study</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>DZone.com: Q&amp;A with Jason Gilmore: The Zend Framework </title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2010 01:12:39 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
On DZone.com today there's a new interview by  Lyndsey Clevesy  with  Jason Gilmore  looking at  the Zend Framework  and some of the general things to expect in coming versions.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11946-DZone.com-QA-with-Jason-Gilmore-The-Zend-Framework-</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11946-DZone.com-QA-with-Jason-Gilmore-The-Zend-Framework-</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Ben Scholzen&#039;s Blog: Modern Application Design - Part 1</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2010 22:13:16 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 Ben Scholzen has started a serial about modern appication design on his blog. As base of this serial he is using his blog source for demonstration. 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11924-Ben-Scholzens-Blog-Modern-Application-Design---Part-1</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11924-Ben-Scholzens-Blog-Modern-Application-Design---Part-1</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Matthew Weier O&#039;Phinney&#039;s Blog: Responding to Different Content Types in RESTful ZF Apps</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2010 21:11:04 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
Continuing on from his  previous   articles  on working with REST in Zend Framework applications (and making the endpoints for a web service)  Matthew Weier O'Phinney  has a new tutorial with the next logical step in the series, automatically  responding to different content types  in your application based on the content-type the client sends.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11925-Matthew-Weier-OPhinneys-Blog-Responding-to-Different-Content-Types-in-RESTful-ZF-Apps</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11925-Matthew-Weier-OPhinneys-Blog-Responding-to-Different-Content-Types-in-RESTful-ZF-Apps</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Michael Kimsal&#039;s Blog: Zend Framework and Doctrine integration - autoloading of doctrine models</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2010 04:56:19 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
 Michael Kimsal  has a new post today looking at using Doctrine models in a Zend Framework application and how to  get them to autoload  when you need them with the help of Zend's Zend_Loader_Autoloader.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11913-Michael-Kimsals-Blog-Zend-Framework-and-Doctrine-integration---autoloading-of-doctrine-models</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11913-Michael-Kimsals-Blog-Zend-Framework-and-Doctrine-integration---autoloading-of-doctrine-models</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Rob Allen&#039;s Blog: Zend Framework, IIS and 500 errors</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2010 04:53:03 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
If you've been using the Zend Framework on a Windows platform (running IIS as the web server) and have been getting some 500 errors and have been left lacking the detail you need on the problem, you should read this  new post from Rob Allen about an IIS setting  that can help you out.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11912-Rob-Allens-Blog-Zend-Framework-IIS-and-500-errors</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11912-Rob-Allens-Blog-Zend-Framework-IIS-and-500-errors</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>ZendCasts.com: Creating Custom Zend_Form Decorators</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2010 21:15:49 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
On ZendCasts.com today there's a new screencast aimed at showing off  custom Zend_Form decorators  for your Zend Framework application.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11901-ZendCasts.com-Creating-Custom-Zend_Form-Decorators</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11901-ZendCasts.com-Creating-Custom-Zend_Form-Decorators</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Connecting Flex 4 and RESTful Web Services using Zend Framework</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2010 19:04:19 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 With Adobe&#8217;s latest incarnation of the Flex Framework and the
								Flash Builder 
								integrated development environment ( IDE ), creating truly engaging front-end 
								clients is now more streamlined. Some of the useful tools and features 
								covered in this article are the Data/Services, Test Operation, and Network 
								Monitor additions to Flash Builder. In this article, I explain how to set up 
								a simple Representational State Transfer ( REST ) service using the Zend 
								Framework 1.9 locally and connect to it in the Flex 4 application. 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11899-Connecting-Flex-4-and-RESTful-Web-Services-using-Zend-Framework</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11899-Connecting-Flex-4-and-RESTful-Web-Services-using-Zend-Framework</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Padraic Brady&#039;s Blog: PHP Framework Benchmarks: Entertaining But Ultimately Useless</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2010 12:50:05 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
In a new post to his blog  Padraic Brady  takes a humorous look at  benchmarking PHP frameworks  in a response to some of the other recent posts from developers on the  Symfony  and  Solar  frameworks.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11873-Padraic-Bradys-Blog-PHP-Framework-Benchmarks-Entertaining-But-Ultimately-Useless</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11873-Padraic-Bradys-Blog-PHP-Framework-Benchmarks-Entertaining-But-Ultimately-Useless</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Adrian Schneider&#039;s Blog: Zend Framework Models - Part 1: Concepts</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2010 18:54:03 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
 Adrian Schneider  has started up a new series of posts on his blog today with part of of his look at  models in the Zend Framework .
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11854-Adrian-Schneiders-Blog-Zend-Framework-Models---Part-1-Concepts</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11854-Adrian-Schneiders-Blog-Zend-Framework-Models---Part-1-Concepts</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Zend Developer Zone - Revamp, Rebuild, Redo, Re-Everything</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2010 20:35:05 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  In January, I returned as editor for the Zend Developer Zone.  At that time I mentioned I would be chasing my goal "To provide a huge value to the PHP community with original, deep, example and situation laden content."  And we have been preparing to start that effort, and in a big way. 

 We will be rebuilding ZDZ from the ground up and in full public view of the community -- to act as a learning experience and a showcase for PHP best practices. 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11811-Zend-Developer-Zone---Revamp-Rebuild-Redo-Re-Everything</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11811-Zend-Developer-Zone---Revamp-Rebuild-Redo-Re-Everything</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Xebee Blog: Test Driven Development with Zend Framework and PHPUnit </title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2010 20:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
On the Xebee blog there's a recent post looking at  test-driven development with the Zend Framework  and  PHPUnit . They show how they work well together and make it simpler to use TTD to create and test your applications.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11805-Xebee-Blog-Test-Driven-Development-with-Zend-Framework-and-PHPUnit-</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11805-Xebee-Blog-Test-Driven-Development-with-Zend-Framework-and-PHPUnit-</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>1st Russian Zend Framework Conference Announced</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2010 23:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 The 1st Russian Zend Framework Conference ( ZFC onf 2010) will take place in Saint-Petersburg, Russia at  the end of March. 

	 An initial list of topics has been decided and the conference is open for registration. 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11781-1st-Russian-Zend-Framework-Conference-Announced</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11781-1st-Russian-Zend-Framework-Conference-Announced</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Managing CSS and JavaScript files within a Zend Framework App</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2010 17:43:17 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 Full design control usually means large, thousand plus line CSS files that equal serious pain when it comes to maintenance or building upon. If you don't namespace your selectors carefully you'll end up paying for it down the road. And heaven forbid you apply a default HTML tag styling. So, ranting aside, how do you maintain flexibility and still keep tidy CSS and JavaScript? My solution is to keep the very same directory/file structure that is used for the application for my CSS and JavaScript. The best part is by writing a very simple view helper, it's super easy to automate the proper head link and script file inclusions.
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11760-Managing-CSS-and-JavaScript-files-within-a-Zend-Framework-App</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11760-Managing-CSS-and-JavaScript-files-within-a-Zend-Framework-App</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Integrating Flickr Photostreams with PHP using the Zend Framework</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2010 02:06:11 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 Like most people with a digital camera, I tend to be a heavy Flickr user. Not only does Flickr make it easy to share my ever-growing photo collection with colleagues and family, but its drag-and-drop photo organizer and geo-tagging features make it easy to quickly categorize and find pictures from, say, my 2003 holiday in Goa. 

	 The really good stuff, though, is hidden behind the scenes. Like many Web 2.0 applications, Flickr exposes its data to the public via a  REST   API , making it possible to develop customized applications that run on top of the base service. This  REST   API  allows access to a number of important functions, including photo searching, tagging and uploading; photoset retrieval; contact retrieval; and panda recommendations. It&#8217;s also pretty easy to integrate this  REST   API  into a  PHP  application &#8211; and this article will show you how! 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11775-Integrating-Flickr-Photostreams-with-PHP-using-the-Zend-Framework</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11775-Integrating-Flickr-Photostreams-with-PHP-using-the-Zend-Framework</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Zend_Paginator with Twitter API and Zend_Cache</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2010 19:46:44 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 Zend_Paginator does a great job of creating pagination for a site. In this blog post I&#8217;m demonstrating how to use Zend_Paginator to easily create pagination of Twitter tweets using Zend_Rest_Client to access the Twitter Services. As a bonus, Zend_Cache is used to store the tweets to make the process more efficient. 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11740-Zend_Paginator-with-Twitter-API-and-Zend_Cache</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11740-Zend_Paginator-with-Twitter-API-and-Zend_Cache</guid> 
          </item>
            </channel>
</rss>
