<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>DevZone - Items tagged as: Zend_Framework_Contributor</title>
        <link>http://devzone.zend.com/</link>
        <description>advancing the art of PHP.  Best practices, samples, articles, news, and community for PHP 4, PHP 5, and beyond.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2010 01:13:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2010 01:13:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <docs>http://devzone.zend.com/tag/Zend_Framework_Contributor/format/rss2.0</docs>     
        <language>en-us</language> 
        <image>
          <title>DevZone - Items tagged as: Zend_Framework_Contributor</title>
          <link>http://devzone.zend.com/</link>
          <url>http://devzone.zend.com/images/devzone_logo4.gif</url>
        </image>
                  <item>
            <title>Announcing February&#039;s ZF Bug Hunting Days</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2010 01:13:06 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 This upcoming Thursday and Friday, 18-19 February 2010, Zend Framework will host its fifth monthly bug hunt. For those of you unfamiliar with the event, each month, we organize the community to help reduce the number of open issues reported against the framework. Past events have netted over 100 issue closures over each two-day period; let's keep up the momentum!
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11835-Announcing-Februarys-ZF-Bug-Hunting-Days</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11835-Announcing-Februarys-ZF-Bug-Hunting-Days</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Announcing December&#039;s ZF Bug Hunt Days</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2009 13:44:35 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
    This upcoming Thursday and Friday, 17-18 December 2009, Zend Framework will
    host its fourth monthly bug hunt. Each month, the community organizes to
    help reduce the number of open issues reported against the framework. Past
    events have netted over 100 issue closures over each two-day period; let's
    keep up the momentum!
 

 
    The rules and rewards are simple: Supply patches or direct commits that
    resolve open issues. The individual who resolves or assists in resolving the
    most issues during the bug hunt wins a Zend Framework t-shirt!
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11480-Announcing-Decembers-ZF-Bug-Hunt-Days</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11480-Announcing-Decembers-ZF-Bug-Hunt-Days</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Results of November&#039;s ZF Bug Hunt Days</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2009 20:54:22 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
    Zend Framework held its third monthly Bug Hunt Days in November on the 19th
    and 20th. During that time, we closed  more than 120 issues  in the tracker,
    many of which made it into the  1.9.6  release
    the following Tuesday.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11421-Results-of-Novembers-ZF-Bug-Hunt-Days</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11421-Results-of-Novembers-ZF-Bug-Hunt-Days</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Announcing November&#039;s ZF Bug Hunting Days</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2009 16:26:25 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
    This upcoming Thursday and Friday, 19-20 November 2009, Zend Framework will
    host its third monthly bug hunt. For those of you unfamiliar with the event,
    each month, we organize the community to help reduce the number of open
    issues reported against the framework. Past events have netted around 100
    issue closures over each two-day period -- and we want to continue the
    momentum.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11326-Announcing-Novembers-ZF-Bug-Hunting-Days</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11326-Announcing-Novembers-ZF-Bug-Hunting-Days</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Results of October&#039;s ZF Bug Hunting Days</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2009 16:28:06 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
    This past Thursday and Friday, 15-16 October 2009, Zend Framework held its
    second monthly bug hunt. Activity started out slow, but picked up
    tremendously on Friday, resulting in initially 100 bugs resolved, though a
    few have been re-opened in the days since. The  full
        list  is available on our issue tracker. Thank you, everyone, for the
    participation, and for keeping this initiative alive and vibrant!
 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11099-Results-of-Octobers-ZF-Bug-Hunting-Days</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11099-Results-of-Octobers-ZF-Bug-Hunting-Days</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Zend Framework October Bug Hunt Starts Today</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2009 13:55:04 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
    As  reported
    last month , Zend Framework has started hosting a monthly "bug hunt": an
    effort to resolve issues against the framework. This month's bug hunt is
    today and tomorrow.
 

 
    The individual who helps resolve or assist in resolving the most issues
    during each month's bug hunt days will receive a Zend Framework t-shirt!
    Last month's winner was Padraic Brady.
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/11058-Zend-Framework-October-Bug-Hunt-Starts-Today</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/11058-Zend-Framework-October-Bug-Hunt-Starts-Today</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Announcing Zend Framework&#039;s Monthly Bug Hunt Days</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2009 18:15:39 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  
    Last Thursday and Friday, the 17th and 18th of September, Zend Framework
    launched its first monthly bug hunt days. The "bug hunt" is actually more of
    a "bug killing" or "bug squashing" event -- the intent is to reduce the
    number of reported issues in the tracker by either fixing them, marking them
    as duplicates, or invalidating them (many issues may stem from lack of
    understanding of the component, invalid reproduce cases, and more). 
 
    
 
    To sweeten the deal, we have also made a small contest out of it: the
    contributor who resolves or assists in resolving the most issues during each
    month's event receives a Zend Framework t-shirt. 
 

            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/10049-Announcing-Zend-Frameworks-Monthly-Bug-Hunt-Days</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/10049-Announcing-Zend-Frameworks-Monthly-Bug-Hunt-Days</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Cahaya CMS 1.0 released!</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2009 18:11:02 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  Cahaya CMS is a new content management system build on Zend framework. It is released under GPLv3 license.   It offers many useful features if you are just an user, a designer or a developer.    For more details, downloads and demo please visit  www.cahaya-project.org   
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/9901-Cahaya-CMS-1.0-released</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/9901-Cahaya-CMS-1.0-released</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>PHP Performance Tips from Stas Malyshev</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2009 13:59:39 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 On his blog, Stas Malyshev (Core Contributor to  PHP  and Zend Employee) has posted a list of  PHP  Performance tips that he wants novices to know about.  He realized that while he had previously panned a post by Google about  PHP  Performance of having lots of incorrect or misleading information, but that he never gave good substitute advice himself. 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/4840-PHP-Performance-Tips-from-Stas-Malyshev</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/4840-PHP-Performance-Tips-from-Stas-Malyshev</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Preview of Windows Azure Support in Zend Framework Released</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2009 19:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 Today a technology preview of upcoming interoperability between Windows Azure and Zend Framework has been announced, in the form of a  PHP   SDK  for Windows Azure.  
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/4809-Preview-of-Windows-Azure-Support-in-Zend-Framework-Released</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/4809-Preview-of-Windows-Azure-Support-in-Zend-Framework-Released</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>ZendCon 2009 Call for Papers is now open!</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2009 20:02:38 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 Zend is proud to announce the dates &amp; location for ZendCon 2009 happening on October 19th-22nd in San Jose, California, and to let everyone know that our Call for Papers is now open!   Let&#8217;s see those great session proposals come in!  Submit early!  Submit often! 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/4558-ZendCon-2009-Call-for-Papers-is-now-open</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/4558-ZendCon-2009-Call-for-Papers-is-now-open</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Zend_Tag_Cloud Screencast</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2009 14:56:03 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 Ben Scholzen, author of Zend_Tag has recorded a screencast to feature the new component. He details the new feature in common use cases, and even in a console application. He also covers using the built in decorators, and how to extend and write your own. 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/4538-Zend_Tag_Cloud-Screencast</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/4538-Zend_Tag_Cloud-Screencast</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title> Database backed Zend_Form elements</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2009 19:55:37 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 A constant blogger of all things Zend Framework, Jani Hartikainen has this time made a post showing how to extend Zend_Form to handle automatically pulling data from the database to fill in your lists. 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/4342--Database-backed-Zend_Form-elements</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/4342--Database-backed-Zend_Form-elements</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Online Resources for Zend Framework</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2009 16:42:16 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 Robert Basic has collected together links to various resources on the web about Zend Framework, blog links, people on twitter, books, and more. 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/4327-Online-Resources-for-Zend-Framework</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/4327-Online-Resources-for-Zend-Framework</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Zend Framework Bug Hunt Day Review</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2008 18:17:02 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                  DragonBe, or Michelangelo van Dam, has posted on  his blog  a  review of the Zend Framework Bug Hunt Day  recently organized by the  phpGG  and  PHPBelgium  user groups. Although not too many bugs were fixed, this was a great community event that highlighted the importance of the community's role in the success of the Zend Framework. 

 "With a turn up of 25 to 30 people we could call this day a success on bringing attention to the need of fixing bugs of huge frameworks. Although no statistics are yet available, I think only a handful of bugs were actually fixed that day. Not much compared to the turn up, but non the less better then none at all." 

 The blog post also includes links to  a presentation given by Juri&#235;n Stutterheim  on how bugs should be processed, and  event pictures . The next Bug Hunt Day will focus on Symfony - have a look at the  official event notice , and sign up if you can! 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/4103-Zend-Framework-Bug-Hunt-Day-Review</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/4103-Zend-Framework-Bug-Hunt-Day-Review</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Zend Framework PHP Bughunting Day</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2008 14:49:31 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 Supporting open-source PHP projects can be done by for example contributing code, writing or translating documentation or by fixing bugs. The latter is not usually the most exciting task, but still is quite important as the amount of bugs is an indication for the overall quality of the project. With this in mind, the Belgian PHP user group PHPBelgium and the Dutch PHP user group, phpGG, have decided to work together and launched a new initiative, called PHP BugHunt Days. 

 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/3964-Zend-Framework-PHP-Bughunting-Day</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/3964-Zend-Framework-PHP-Bughunting-Day</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Adobe to contribute AMF support to Zend Framework</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2008 14:09:26 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 There is big news in the Zend Framework world this morning. Zend and Adobe are working together to put support for AMF into the framework.  

 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/3743-Adobe-to-contribute-AMF-support-to-Zend-Framework</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/3743-Adobe-to-contribute-AMF-support-to-Zend-Framework</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Zend_Acl and MVC Integration Part II (Advanced Use)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2008 13:39:21 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 In the previous article we saw how to setup our Zend_Acl instance and how to attach it to the MVC environment (by using the Front Controller Plugin), but what about setting another action for the denied access, or how does an article be edited only by its owner?, this, and some more is what we are going to see in the following examples. 

 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/3510-Zend_Acl-and-MVC-Integration-Part-II-Advanced-Use</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/3510-Zend_Acl-and-MVC-Integration-Part-II-Advanced-Use</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Erwin Earley writes on PHP and the Zend Framework</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2008 18:34:31 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 If you are in the i5 community then you know the name Erwin Earley. Recently Erwin published an article on itjungle.com on using the Zend Framework.  Click on inside and let&#8217;s take a look. 

 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/3675-Erwin-Earley-writes-on-PHP-and-the-Zend-Framework</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/3675-Erwin-Earley-writes-on-PHP-and-the-Zend-Framework</guid> 
          </item>
                  <item>
            <title>Zend_Acl and MVC Integration Part I (Basic Use)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2008 14:02:29 +0000</pubDate>
            <description>
                 	 So, what is wrong with Zend_Acl and the current MVC implementation in the Zend Framework? there is nothing wrong, it is just that it gets not too obvious for developers how to achieve an optimal integration between these two important parts of the framework. 

 
            </description>
            <link>http://devzone.zend.com/article/3509-Zend_Acl-and-MVC-Integration-Part-I-Basic-Use</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devzone.zend.com/article/3509-Zend_Acl-and-MVC-Integration-Part-I-Basic-Use</guid> 
          </item>
            </channel>
</rss>
