<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<applications>
    <application>
        <company>StormTide Digital Studios Inc.</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            <a href="http://neutrality.ca" target="apps">Neutrality.ca</a>, Canada's largest Net Neutrality Campaign,
            is a multi-lingual site based on Zend Framework. It has been featured on the National news and relates to
            a significant policy debate at the highest levels of government.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>Apprize360 Intelligence</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            One of our production sites is webArgos (<a href="http://www.webargos.com"
            target="apps">www.webargos.com</a>). It uses a lot of the Zend Framework components, including Acl, Auth,
            Config, Controller, Date, Db, Json, Mail, and Registry. It has guest, client, and admin modules to
            separate the functionality of each. Acl and Auth are used together to control access to each part. Db
            interacts with a PostgreSQL database, and we use Mail to automatically send notifications to our users. We
            use Zend_Json to send AJAX responses to the browser that are handled by our JavaScript. A couple other
            production applications that use Zend Framework are <a href="http://personal.apprize360.com"
            target="apps">personal.apprize360.com</a> and <a href="http://www.dewoods.com"
            target="apps">www.dewoods.com</a>. We also have a couple other sites that use parts of the framework,
            which we plan to upgrade at some point to make use of the entire framework.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>Neu.de</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            We have used various components of Zend Framework for the relaunch of <a href="http://neu.de"
            target="apps">Neu.de</a>, one of the biggest online dating platforms in Germany. Neu.de has average number
            of users of something around 7000. We have actually used Zend_XmlRpc_Client, Zend_Http_Client,
            Zend_Session, Zend_Filter and Zend_Validator.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>Voxtronic Technology</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            Multiple WebApplications (closed source) for speech recording and data collection services. All in
            production, <a href="http://voxlog.voxtronic.com" target="apps">voxlog.voxtronic.com</a> (demo demo). Uses
            Zend_Locale, Zend_Date, Zend_Db, Zend_Session, Zend_Translate, Zend_Cache, Zend_XmlRpc, Zend_Exception,
            Zend_Mail, Zend_Log, Zend_Validate, and Zend_View.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>None</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            I'm developing a commercial financial system, which will consist of core applications for General Ledger,
            Accounts Payable, and Accounts Receivable, as well as a suite of other important line-of-business
            applications that will integrate with the core apps. The system is targeted at local governments and small
            to medium businesses. Uses: ACL, Auth, Cache, Db, Locale, Log, Mail, Registry, Session...
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>ContentWatch, Inc</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            See <a href="http://www.contentwatch.com" target="apps">http://www.contentwatch.com</a> and <a
            href="http://www.netnanny.com" target="apps">http://www.netnanny.com</a>. We are using Zend Framework
            to power not only our public website and online store, but our partner portal and customer relationship
            management as well. In conjunction with our own in-house libraries has made development and deployment
            much easier.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>Varien</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            We are currently working on the next generation open source eCommerce platform, Magento. It is based on
            Zend Framework and pending to be released in August, 2007.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>Peo Development Group</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            I've developed Peo CMS which is content management system based on ZF 1.0.0RC1. It handles content
            management, users management, newsletter, and everything is internationalized. Two sites created using Peo
            CMS: <a href="http://yellow.pl/" target="apps">http://yellow.pl/</a> &amp; <a href=
            "http://nasylwestra.pl/" target="apps">http://nasylwestra.pl/</a>. Uses: Zend_Acl, Zend_Auth, Zend_Cache,
            Zend_Config, Zend_Controller, Zend_Db, Zend_Debug, Zend_Log, Zend_Loader, Zend_Locale, Zend_Mail,
            Zend_Session, Zend_Translate, Zend_View
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>qbus | websolutions</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            Legal software for a governmental organization. Uses: MVC components with Zend_DB (Oracle), Zend_Auth and
            Zend_Acl
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company><![CDATA[<a href="http://12ga.com" target="apps">12ga.com</a>]]></company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            Simple Poll system. Users can create, edit polls. There are three types of answers: radio,checkbox and
            input (open question). Uses: Zend_Db_*, MVC
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company><![CDATA[Quatrain D&eacute;veloppement]]></company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            PAGE - Supplies ordering system for the 500 primary schools of the city of Marseille. Allows schools
            headmasters and teachers to order stationeries and other items from the different suppliers endorsed by
            the City. More than 2000 users spending 3 M Euros. In production since the beginning of May 2007. Uses:
            Zend_Db, Zend_Json, Zend_Controller. Plans to use Zend_Db_Table.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company><![CDATA[Quatrain D&eacute;veloppement]]></company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            GUEPA - SSO application used by PAGE and other applications to come. Contains all information and
            privileges of schools members for the city of Marseille. Queried via SOAP. in Production.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company><![CDATA[Event Community <a href="http://portey.de" target="apps">portey.de</a>]]></company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            The current available version is over 5 years old. We are currently developing a complete rewrite with ZF.
            It will become a social event/invitations community. Uses: Zend_Cache, Zend_Controller, Zend_Date,
            Zend_Db, Zend_Feed, Zend_Filter, Zend_Filter_Input, Zend_Mail, Zend_Registry, Zend_Validate, Zend_View
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>World Tourism Solutions</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            Email marketing software, providing the required functionality to allow non-technical users to compose
            html based mail messages and to manage by themselves lists of contacts
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>Baldock Web Development</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            <a href="http://www.esphotography.co.uk/" target="apps">http://www.esphotography.co.uk/</a> Shopping Cart,
            CMS, Horses for Sale adverts pages, Contact email form and MySQL based sessions all fully built using ZF.
            Uses: MVC, Db (and Db_Table), Session, Registry, Config and Mail.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>Enargi Consulting</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            <a href="http://hitask.com/" target="apps">http://hitask.com</a> A Web2.0 task management site. Uses:
            Mail, Feeds.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>Maya's Mom, Inc.</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            Maya's Mom, the premiere social network site for parents is built using Zend Framework. <a
            href="http://www.mayasmom.com/" target="apps">http://www.mayasmom.com/</a> Uses: The overall Zend
            Framework structure for routing, controllers as well as Zend DB for data access. Zend Framework is
            flexible and allows us to use our pre-existing Smarty templates for the view.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>Big Room Ventures Ltd.</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            One Wishlist (<a href="http://onewishlist.net/" target="apps">http://onewishlist.net/</a>) - a universal
            wishlist website that isn&rsquo;t tied to individual online shops. Create a wishlist, tell your friends
            and receive the gifts you want. Your list can include gifts from all online and offline stores, even from
            the special gift shop at the end of the road.<br /> The site was originally built using version 0.7 of the
            Zend framework. We keep a test version updated to work with the latest version of the framework and will
            be launching this as soon after the 1.0 release of the framework as we can. The site uses the MVC
            structure from the framework, the registry and one or two other bits. We will be using Zend_Service and
            some of the specific services in the future. We use or own database access layer; because it was already
            developed, we like it, and it was easy to integrate it with Zend Framework.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>M6</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            I used Zend Framework to develop a document managing system (upload/download, user permissions, etc)
            and it's currently in production on the company's intranet. Uses: MVC parts, registry, config, db/tables,
            log and more.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>PHPDeveloper.org</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            The community news site PHPDeveloper.org is run entirely on the framework. <a
            href="http://www.phpdeveloper.org/" target="apps">http://www.phpdeveloper.org</a>
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>SUN Area Career &amp; Technology Center</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            Used ZFW to build an intranet for a high school. Uses: Zend_Controller, Zend_Session, Zend_Acl, Zend_Auth,
            and Zend_Cache, Zend_Log, and Zend_Validate.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>Personal Fund Drive</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            An app for non-profits to enable them to create and run fund drives. Members can create a personalized
            version of the drive and email friends/associates, asking them to sponsor them and contribute online to
            the fund drive. Uses Zend_Controller, Zend_Acl, Zend_Date, Zend_Auth, Zend_Config, and Zend_Registry. <a
            href="http://www.personalfunddrive.com/" target="apps">http://www.personalfunddrive.com/</a>
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>Lionite LTD.</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            I have used the framework as the basis for my startup, "Octabox", which is a web platform for online
            productivity, sharing and collaboration. It is in private alpha at the moment, and can be found at <a
            href="http://www.octabox.com/" target="apps">http://www.octabox.com</a>. Uses: The entire Zend_Db class
            hierarchy, Zend_Filter and Zend_Validate through Zend_Filter_Input, The entire Zend_Controller class
            hierarchy, Zend_View, Zend_Search_Lucene, Zend_Session, Zend_Auth, Zend_Json, Zend_Registry. I plan to add
            in the near future extensive use of the Zend_Cache and Zend_Acl components.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>Eurotransplant</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            The NTS (Dutch transplant foundation) uses an application built with ZF to register information off
            deceased patients in Dutch hospitals. We have used the ZF controller and view components with a custom
            model implementation based on a php version of iBatis. The application will be in production from july
            2007.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>USVN.info</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            A web interface to manage subversion repositories. <a href="http://www.usvn.info/"
            target="apps">http://www.usvn.info</a>
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.sega4you.com/" target="apps">http://www.sega4you.com</a>]]></company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            The website is owned by one of the major paper-based newspapers in Bulgaria. It is a general classifieds
            website based on ZF 0.9.3. Used: Zend_DB, Zend_DB_Select, Zend_Registry, Zend_Cache, Zend_StripTags, etc.
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
    <application>
        <company>die hoflieferanten</company>
        <description>
            <![CDATA[
            Newsletter System for business customers of the novotel Hotel Group in Berlin/Germany. <a
            href="http://www.novotel-berlin.com/" target="apps">http://www.novotel-berlin.com</a>
            ]]>
        </description>
    </application>
</applications>
